<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>quantomistro</title>
    <link>https://quantomistro.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on quantomistro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2020 18:00:47 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://quantomistro.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>GUI With JavaFX (1)</title>
      <link>https://quantomistro.github.io/posts/gui-with-javafx-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2020 18:00:47 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quantomistro.github.io/posts/gui-with-javafx-1/</guid>
      <description>For International Baccalaureate (IB) students, around 20% of their grade (i think?) depends on their Internal Assessments (IAs) in each course. Each course has its own requirements for the IA. For Computer Science students, the IA is basically finding a &amp;ldquo;client&amp;rdquo; with problem X and then building a program to solve that problem for them - an exercise in software development. Now at any given time, I usually have a list of cool ideas and programs I want to build someday to make the world a happier place - but none of them were risk-free enough for an assignment that would account for 20% of my final grade.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://quantomistro.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 15:37:45 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quantomistro.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>this blog I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what to write here? It&amp;rsquo;s just another blog. I write about my opinions and likes and dislikes and put them here. Expect mostly CS-related stuff here, mixed in with some of my occasional stupid random thoughts that must be shared with the internet*.
me My name&amp;rsquo;s M------ S----, but I go by quantomistro in most places on the internet. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember why I chose &amp;ldquo;quantomistro&amp;rdquo;, but I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure it involved some random word generators and my interest in astronomy and quantum-anything.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting a blog</title>
      <link>https://quantomistro.github.io/posts/starting-a-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2019 00:38:43 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://quantomistro.github.io/posts/starting-a-blog/</guid>
      <description>Sometime during 2018 I had the very original idea of starting my own blog. So, I started one, and then forgot about it, and now I&amp;rsquo;ve started another one. Thankfully, my previous experience had taught me just how hard it can be to think of new ideas for blog posts, which is why I came prepared this time.
For my first blog post, I&amp;rsquo;ll be talking about how I set up this blog.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>